okay so recently like in the past two
days or so Sam Harris put out a new
podcast where he was contemplating
what's up what's going on and in that
particular piece of content he raised
the question or proposed the possibility
that we are losing our minds and this
made me think one of the frames that
I've used in the past comes from
Marshall McLuhan and what I'd like to do
is address that particular frame in this
in the context of are we losing our
minds and in fact in Simpsons are we in
the process of transitioning between one
kind of mind and another kind of mind so
we're both losing and gaining and that
is that maybe a deeper explanation of
what's really happening so the context
the McLuhan piece is this notion of one
mind so I'm not going to go into exactly
what mind is but the idea that mind is
in some very fundamental sense not
significantly preconditioned by a notion
of what extension or body is which is to
say that mind is like a fluid a vessel
that fills the the possibility of how
mind relates with the world so
perception and interaction or agency are
mediated by some kinds of constructs of
extensions our hands our eyeballs but
also like eyeglasses or telescope this
video if I Drive a car or this is an
extension of self extension of body
extension of capacity to interact with
members and perceive experience and mind
fits into that it flows into it and has
a very sort of ambivalent sense frankly
of what our body is but rather is very
deeply connected trying to figure out
how to be most fundamentally in
relationship with what the body can do
okay so so for example a really easy
metaphor that I've found makes a lot of
sense to me is the notion of when you're
driving a car let's say you've got a
little you know a little Honda car and
you've been driving it for years so
you're very connected with it it makes a
lot of sense
you're very fluid you can pull into
parking spots you can parallel park
you can change lanes and there's a deep
of connectedness to it so for example if
somebody Nick's the car
the response is he hit me not he hit my
car you're fed sense of self in the
sense of carving coextensive and then
you rent an RV a big one like a 36-foot
you know heavy heavy big RV and it feels
odd you feel out of sorts you feel a
weird sense of not being in charge of in
some sense your own body
you can't feel where your edges are you
can't feel your front and back are and
it's very disconcerting you accelerate
and it doesn't accelerate in the same
way you break it isn't break in the same
way I think that's kind of the metaphor
the sense of embodiment is associated
with the mechanisms of our extension ok
so given that context the things that we
call media things like say broadcast
television and books and the internet
and cell phones are particularly pointed
in this context media deeply deeply
affect in particular our capacities for
for perception of reality of experience
and many also very important ways our
ways of expression particularly to other
minds when that's crucial the other mind
piece of is important it's that it's the
fabric through which we're able to be in
relationship with other minds and
therefore to have a collective
perception of reality and a collective
agents in reality collective
intelligence
so our media is changing my media has
changed we're actually in the midst of
the consequence of the change there was
a long period of time more or less the
context in which the baby boomers were
born and raised that was strictly
dominated by a particular kind of media
television mostly this television has a
couple of characteristics that I think
matter in this context one is what's the
thing was the aspect of body that's
being modified by television and it's
audio-visual television is basically
imagination it's fantasy
it's our capacity to interrelate with
story but almost no agency and we can't
actually go in and change the story
isn't
you know if you see a small child
watching TV the child will try to
interact the TV smile point move the TV
doesn't interact with a child so it
creates a really weird felt sense of
being deeply non-agenda kin relationship
with experience and of course television
can radically super saturate our
sensibility of what experiences the
television can be much more dramatic it
can be much more beautiful it can be
much like the people on TV are more
beautiful than the people you see in
day-to-day life the events and
experiences on TV a more intense than
the immense experiences of day-to-day
life so it creates a biasing effect
towards narrative towards story towards
dramatization and away from embodied
experience so it's it's okay that's the
two characteristics another one is it's
it's a highly asymmetric and I mean that
both in the sense of agency the story
flows at you and it flows it has no
memory by the way you know the thing
that just happened maybe you remember it
that you're so overwhelmed by the
sensorial that your memory is a tiny
piece of this big flux it flows at you
and you don't really flow back at it but
you can change the channel but that's a
bit like your your agency is to select
which stream that flows through you very
little to no capacity to actually
interact back and shift and engage and
it's also a symmetric in the sense of
there's some small number of express
errs in the television domain that can
the boomers hear there was like three
four if you include public television
she probably shouldn't and a huge number
of audience right so you have this
feeling like maybe in the in the early
80s before cable really mattered that
like monoculture like we all watched the
same show so we're very entrained to a
very small set of ideas and artifacts
and we all watched the same three big
news shows every night and by the way
almost everyone did and that creates an
effect both in terms of the felt sense
of fantasy right you're you're somehow
having a conversation again in the news
kiss it's as if Walter Cronkite is in
everybody's living room but we're not
all in his living room I saw that both
happen on the one hand this is fantastic
projection of someone into your
consciousness who's not present in other
ways
and this massive asymmetry okay so that
creates a kind of mind this is the idea
your mind has full boomer Minds in
particular and Gen X reminds to a lesser
extent flow into that media landscape
and we shouldn't underestimate the
amount of impact mind our minds have
been very very television and we spent a
lot of time watching TV in many
cases more than we spent in almost any
other domain of our lives and so that's
important in the way that our mind is
right there with the mind has shifted
and flow to fill a particular shape just
like that Honda but now we've switched
right now much more of our attention is
spent in a very different media domain
we're spending more and more time in
this thing called social media social
media is different social media has is
much more symmetric not fully symmetric
you know people big Twitter
personalities your youtubers have a lot
more followers than the average person
but the average person has more than
zero I might have five or seven so
there's kind of a higher-level asymmetry
and certainly there's an interactivity
at the notion that every comment that
someone makes has a response available
and generally expected but if you post
something on Facebook the expectation is
there will be some kind of interaction
it's not a strictly broadcast medium
flowing boo out another key element
which i think is deeply underestimated
which is that if you think about the the
cognitive functions that are most up
regularly or almost uniquely up
regulated in this new kind of mind it's
memory this is by the way I am taking
very specifically from the guys for at
the Center for digital life and the
McLuhan people they identified this as
crucial the Internet is they say never
forgets right so while our mind in train
with things like television and radio it
just a flux and our memory is is very
best partial and not particularly
relevant and certainly the medium has no
memory I mean in this case the Internet
is like a gigantic cybernetic adjunct to
our memory we remember now everything
every event that happens every tweet
that occurs every Facebook posted occurs
somewhere and generally speaking can be
accessed and also all the events that
occur all the facts like we now have
this large capacity to recall facts we
just didn't have back then if you're a
millennial or Gen Z you really don't
have as a meaningful connection with the
experience of being a Boomer or a gen
Xer where a question comes up like
you're sitting around the dinner table
and somebody has a question about some
fact you know who was the the president
of Argentina in 1870 some fact like that
nobody knows and there's no way to find
out like imagine that to be in a context
where it was actually effectively
impossible to be able to access a
particular piece of information so the
mind had to relate to that the really
mind focused on up-regulated on things
like telling good stories in TV era
recognizing that facts didn't really
matter that much because most people
couldn't check your facts
quality rhetoric quality persuasion now
that's powerful stuff whereas in the in
the ear of the internet it's a different
vibe alright there's definitely ways of
fact-checking
there's definitely ways we could put a
research and dig deeper and find out
what's going on and create maps of the
of the story of what's actually going on
in reality now of course there's
problematics there's problems and people
being able to generate vast amounts of
information and the challenges of
figuring out how to sort through the
noise to get to signal is non-trivial
it's a major challenge in the in the age
of the internet but it's different
alright so yes a lot of the things that
people like Tristan Harris call out
which I think Sam Harris's is a relation
is riffing with having to do with things
like dopamine addiction and the way that
attention jacking in asymmetric
relationships with AI which are also
very characteristic pieces of this
medium are critical we need to
understand those but what I'm talking
about I think is also critical that to
be able to grasp the way that our mind
flows into and becomes a data into a
particular capacity for perception and
interaction with experience and in
particular with other minds and how that
forms a kind of mind that has
expectations and assumptions and
optimizes for certain kinds of behaviors
that are upregulated in the in one
environment and then it finds itself in
a very different environment so we are
yes losing our minds we have in fact in
many ways lost
Carmine's we are no longer operating in
a broadcast consciousness we're now
operating in this new kind of
consciousness which we could call I
suppose a digital or a connected or an
Internet consciousness which is just
different and we haven't figured out how
to operate in that consciousness yet and
our social structures the institutions
that we form the the notions of how we
do things like say journalism or science
or politics or economics are being
dragged along right that they evolved in
the context of broadcast mind seeking
how to most effectively operate in the
dynamics of how that kind of mind
expressed itself how that kind of mind
perceived and the possibilities have
changed and so they're no longer adapted
so the social structures our main ways
dragged along by the fundamental
psychology that is itself dragged along
by the technical media infrastructure is
that the whole story no but it's an
important part of the story and if
you've got it you have more capacity to
have effective agency in the world that
we're swimming in